A Guide to the Papers of David J. Toscano, 1947-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of David J. Toscano 1947-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12690
The collection consists of 3,300 items (13 Hollinger boxes, ca. 5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by David J. Toscano, Charlottesville, Virginia, on October 23, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
David J. Toscano received his Ph.D. in sociology from Boston College in 1979 and subsequently taught at several colleges and universities including James Madison University and the University of Virginia. He first ran for public office in 1982 when he was put forward as a Citizen's Party candidate for the General Assembly-a race which he lost. In 1990 Toscano was elected to the Charlottesville City Council on the Democratic Party ticket; he served his first term from 1990-1994 and his second term from 1994-1998. From 1994-1996 he served a two-year term as Mayor of the City of Charlottesville.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of David J. Toscano, a Democrat who served on the Charlottesville City Council from 1990-1998 and was the Mayor of Charlottesville from 1994-1996. During his tenure he oversaw a multitude of issues including Charlottesville town reversion; the Meadow Creek Parkway; revitalization of West Main Street; cable television; fire and rescue services; the landfill and recycling; revenue sharing; transportation improvement; the attraction of "hi-tech" business; and a vision statement for Charlottesville 2025. Although he left City Council after two terms, Toscano remains active in Charlottesville politics.
The collection consists of 3,300 items (13 Hollinger boxes, ca. 5 linear feet), and mainly contains Toscano's correspondence, minutes from City Council Meetings, video recordings of city Council Meetings, collected papers relating to various Charlottesville issues during Toscano's tenure, and materials from Toscano' election campaigns. Documents in the collection range from 1947 to 2003, although the bulk occur between 1990 and 2002, with most of the materials in the collection coming from Charlottesville, Virginia.
Box 1 contains clippings of newspaper and magazine articles featuring Toscano, including coverage of his election campaigns.
Box 2 contains correspondence from Toscano's time as City Councilor.
Box 3 contains correspondence from Toscann's time as City Councilor as well as his Housing Authority correspondence.
Box 4 contains correspondence from Toscano's tenure as the mayor of Charlottesville. Also, it contains materials form his elections including advertisements, buttons and bumper stickers, Democratic candidate information, community feedback, contact databases, and delegate slates.
Box 5 contains materials relating to cable issues including contact lists, correspondence, notes and agendas form meetings, and questions that were asked at public forums. It also contains materials on economic development issues, education issues, illegal drugs, and the housing issues. There are also papers from the redrafting of the Charlottesville fire contract including background research, clippings, notes and minutes from meetings, presentations, and proposals and agreements regarding the fire contract.
Box 6 contains papers relating to landfill and recycling issues including clippings and publications, letters, notes, reports and memos, reports on the privatization of waste management, and settlement agreements. It also contains papers regarding the Meadow Creek Parkway, including background research, correspondence, community forums, notes, reports and memos, and a study of roadway alternatives. There are also papers relating to the Reinventing Government campaign of 1994-1995, including clippings, notes, conferences and presentations, and reports and memos.
Box 7 contains papers regarding retirement issues and revenue sharing. It also contains papers from Charlottesville Town Reversion including alternatives and questions to reversion; background information on annexation and the reversion process; case studies; information on the blue ribbon commission; financial documents; correspondence; impact reports regarding commonwealth attorneys, finances, housing, the Muller Report, and other miscellaneous reports.
Box 8 contains more papers from the reversion issue, including impact reports regarding schools, staffing, voting districts; joint Charlottesville-Albemarle meetings; legal documents; information about Mays and Valentine, the law firm representing the City of Charlottesville; notes, names and contact lists, the petition and proposed terms of reversion; papers form the planning commission; and presentations on reversion.
Box 9 contains the remainder of the reversion issue papers, including reports by William Lucy, a member of the Town Reversion Committee, publications and clippings, reversion resolutions, and information on voluntary settlement. It also contains a strategy issues workbook from 2000 that details Charlottesville's agenda regarding a variety of issues. Papers relating to technology issues are also in this box, including case stuies, clippings, contact lists, correspondence, minutes and agendas from meetings, notes, and reports and memos. This box also contains materials relating to tourism, tobacco taxes, and the Second Street crossing.
Box 10 contains papers regarding transportation issues, including papers from the Charlottesville/Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization's improvement program, papers on Charlottesville/Albemarle Transportation and Community Options (CATO), memo and reports, notes, and presentations and guides. There are also papers regarding water issues, the Water Street parking garage, and the University of Virginia. It also includes papers from the revitalization of West Main Street, including agendas and schedules, clippings, correspondence, maps, memos, notes, and memos.
Box 11 contains additional papers regarding the revitalization of West Main Street, including notes and reports. It also contains the minutes from Charlottesville City Council Meetings from 1990-1993.
Box 12 contains the minutes from City Council meetings between 1994 and 1999.
Box 13 contains the minutes from City Council Meetings from 2000-2002. It also includes a Myers-Briggs test taken by Toscano, photographs of Toscano and Charlottesville, press releases, and speeches made by Toscano. It also contains information regarding Charlottesville's Vision: Charlottesville 2025 campaign, including background information, forums, notes, and the campaign's themes and principles.
Arrangement
This collection is organized alphabetically by subject matter, and then chronologically within folders.
Contents List
- Clippings 1982 (Drawer-folder 1:1)
- Clippings 1989-2002, n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Correspondence: City Council 1990 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Correspondence: City Council 1991 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Correspondence: City Council 1992 Jan-Jun (Box-folder 2:3)
- Correspondence: City Council 1992 Jul-Dec (Box-folder 2:4)
- Correspondence: City Council 1993 Jan-Jun (Box-folder 2:5)
- Correspondence: City Council 1993 Jul-Dec (Box-folder 2:6)
- Correspondence: City Council 1994 Jan-Apr (Box-folder 2:7)
- Correspondence: City Council 1994 May-Dec (Box-folder 2:8)
- Correspondence: City Council 1996 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Correspondence: City Council 1997 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Correspondence: City Council 1998 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Correspondence: City Council 1999 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Correspondence: City Council 2000 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Correspondence: City Council 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Correspondence: Housing Authority 1990-1994 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Correspondence: Mayor 1994 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Correspondence: Mayor 1995 (Box-folder 4:2)
- Correspondence: Mayor 1996 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Elections: Advertising 1990-1991, n.d. (Box-folder 4:4)
- Elections: Candidate Information, Democrats 1980-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 4:5)
- Elections: Community Feedback 1990, n.d. (Box-folder 4:6)
- Elections: Contact Databases 1980-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 4:7)
- Elections: Delegate Slates, Delegates n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)
- Elections: Financial Records 1990 (Box-folder 4:9)
- Elections: Miscellaneous 1990, n.d. (Box-folder 4:10)
- Financial Reports, Budgets: City Council 1991-1998 (Box-folder 4:11)
- Financial Reports, Budgets: City Council 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4:12)
- Financial Reports, Budgets: City Council 2001-2003 (Box-folder 4:13)
- Issues: Cable: Contact List n.d. (Box-folder 5:1)
- Issues: Cable: Correspondence 1983-1993, n.d. (Box-folder 5:2)
- Issues: Cable: Notes, Agendas 1992 (Box-folder 5:3)
- Issues: Cable: Public Hearing-Questions/Comments n.d. (Box-folder 5:4)
- Issues: Child Development n.d. (Box-folder 5:5)
- Issues: Economic Development 1991-2001 (Box-folder 5:6)
- Issues: Education 1996-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 5:7)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Background Information, Data 1997-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 5:8)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Clippings 1985-1996 (Box-folder 5:9)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Notes and Minutes 1999-2001, n.d. (Box-folder 5:10)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Presentations 1996-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 5:11)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Proposals and Agreements 1996-1998 (Box-folder 5:12)
- Issues: Fire Contract: Proposals and Agreements 1999-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 5:13)
- Issues: Illegal Drugs n.d. (Box-folder 5:14)
- Issues: Housing Authority 1990 (Box-folder 5:15)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Clippings, Publications 1989-1993, n.d. (Box-folder 6:1)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Letters 1991-1994 (Box-folder 6:2)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Notes 1991 (Box-folder 6:3)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Privatization Reports n.d. (Box-folder 6:4)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Reports, Memos 1991-2001 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Issues: Landfill and Recycling: Settlement Agreement 2000 (Box-folder 6:6)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Background Information 1947-1999 (Box-folder 6:7)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Correspondence 1997-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 6:8)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Forums 1998-1999 (Box-folder 6:9)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Notes 1999, n.d. (Box-folder 6:10)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Reports and Memos 1997-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 6:11)
- Issues: Meadow Creek Parkway: Study of Roadway Alternatives 1999 (Box-folder 6:12)
- Issues: Reinventing Government: Clippings, Publications 1994-1995, n.d. (Box-folder 6:13)
- Issues: Reinventing Government: Notes-Toscano 1994 (Box-folder 6:14)
- Issues: Reinventing Government: Presentations, Conferences 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 6:15)
- Issues: Reinventing Government: Reports and Memos 1994-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 6:16)
- Issues: Retirement 1998 (Box-folder 7:1)
- Issues: Revenue Sharing 1994 (Box-folder 7:2)
- Issues: Reversion: Alternatives, Questions 1994-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 7:3)
- Issues: Reversion: Background Information: Annexation n.d. (Box-folder 7:4)
- Issues: Reversion: Background Information: Case Studies 1988-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 7:5)
- Issues: Reversion: Background Information: Reversion Process 1993-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 7:6)
- Issues: Reversion: Blue Ribbon Commission 1997 (Box-folder 7:7)
- Issues: Reversion: Budget, Expenses 1994-1997 (Box-folder 7:8)
- Issues: Reversion: Correspondence 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 7:9)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Commonwealth Attorneys 1996-1997 (Box-folder 7:10)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Financial 1990-2002, n.d. (Box-folder 7:11)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Housing 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 7:12)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 7:13)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Muller Report 1995-1997 (Box-folder 7:14)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Schools 1995-1996 (Box-folder 8:1)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Staffing n.d. (Box-folder 8:2)
- Issues: Reversion: Impact Reports: Voting 1996-1997 (Box-folder 8:3)
- Issues: Reversion: Joint City-County Meetings 1980-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 8:4)
- Issues: Reversion: Legal Documents 1994-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 8:5)
- Issues: Reversion: Mays and Valentine Information (Law Firm n.d. (Box-folder 8:6)
- Issues: Reversion: Names 1996, n.d. (Box-folder 8:7)
- Issues: Reversion: Notes--Toscano 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 8:8)
- Issues: Reversion: Petition, Proposed Terms 1996 (Box-folder 8:9)
- Issues: Reversion: Planning Commission, Urban Development 1994-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 8:10)
- Issues: Reversion: Presentations 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 8:11)
- Issues: Reversion: Reports by William Lucy 1996, n.d. (Box-folder 9:1)
- Issues: Reversion: Publications, Clippings 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 9:2)
- Issues: Reversion: Resolutions 1996-1999 (Box-folder 9:3)
- Issues: Reversion: Voluntary Settlement 1997-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 9:4)
- Issues: Second Street Crossing 2000-2001 (Box-folder 9:5)
- Issues: Strategy Issues Workbook 2000 (Box-folder 9:6)
- Issues: Strategy Issues Workbook 2000 (Box-folder 9:7)
- Issues: Technology: Case Study 1998 (Box-folder 9:8)
- Issues: Technology: Clippings 1998-1999 (Box-folder 9:9)
- Issues: Technology: Contact List 1998-1999 (Box-folder 9:10)
- Issues: Technology: Correspondence 1998-1999 (Box-folder 9:11)
- Issues: Technology: Minutes and Agendas 1998-1999 (Box-folder 9:12)
- Issues: Technology: Notes 1998, n.d. (Box-folder 9:13)
- Issues: Technology: Reports and Memos 1998-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 9:14)
- Issues: Tobacco Taxes 1993, n.d. (Box-folder 9:15)
- Issues: Tourism n.d. (Box-folder 9:16)
- Issues: Transportation: Charlottesville/Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization-Improvement Program 2002 (Box-folder 10:1)
- Issues: Transportation: Charlottesville/Albemarle Transportation and Community Options (CATO 2000 (Box-folder 10:2)
- Issues: Transportation: Memos and Reports 1994-1999 (Box-folder 10:3)
- Issues: Transportation: Memos and Reports 2000-2002, n.d. (Box-folder 10:4)
- Issues: Transportation: Notes 1994, n.d. (Box-folder 10:5)
- Issues: Transportation: Presentations, Guides 1993-1995 (Box-folder 10:6)
- Issues: University of Virginia 1990-1997 (Box-folder 10:7)
- Issues: Water 2001, n.d. (Box-folder 10:8)
- Issues: Water Street Parking Garage 1990 (Box-folder 10:9)
- Issues: West Main: Agendas and Schedules 1992-1993, n.d. (Box-folder 10:10)
- Issues: West Main: Clippings 1988-994, n.d. (Box-folder 10:11)
- Issues: West Main: Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box-folder 10:12)
- Issues: West Main: Maps 1991 (Box-folder 10:13)
- Issues: West Main: Memos 1991-1992 Sep (Box-folder 10:14)
- Issues: West Main: Memos 1992 Oct-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 10:15)
- Issues: West Main: Notes 1992, n.d. (Box-folder 11:1)
- Issues: West Main: Reports 1991-1992 (Box-folder 11:2)
- Issues: West Main: Reports 1993-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 11:3)
- Minutes: City Council 1990 (Box-folder 11:4)
- Minutes: City Council 1991 (Box-folder 11:5)
- Minutes: City Council 1992 (Box-folder 11:6)
- Minutes: City Council 1993 (Box-folder 11:7)
- Minutes: City Council 1994 (Box-folder 12:1)
- Minutes: City Council 1995 (Box-folder 12:2)
- Minutes: City Council 1996 (Box-folder 12:3)
- Minutes: City Council 1997 (Box-folder 12:4)
- Minutes: City Council 1998 (Box-folder 12:5)
- Minutes: City Council 1999 Jan-1999 Jun (Box-folder 12:6)
- Minutes: City Council 1999 Jul-1999 Dec (Box-folder 12:7)
- Minutes: City Council 2000 Jan- 2000 Jun (Box-folder 13:1)
- Minutes: City Council 2000 Jul-2000 Dec (Box-folder 13:2)
- Minutes: City Council 2001 (Box-folder 13:3)
- Minutes: City Council 2002 (Box-folder 13:4)
- Myers-Briggs Test 1990 Sep 16 (Box-folder 13:5)
- Photographs 2000, n.d. (Box-folder 13:6)
- Press Releases 1990, n.d. (Box-folder 13:7)
- Speeches 1984-1994 (Box-folder 13:8)
- Speeches 1995 (Box-folder 13:9)
- Speeches 1996-2002, n.d. (Box-folder 13:10)
- Vision: Charlottesville 2025: Background Info, Forums 1996-1998 (Box-folder 13:11)
- Vision: Charlottesville 2025: Notes-Toscano 1996, n.d. (Box-folder 13:12)
- Vision: Charlottesville 2025: Vision Themes, Principles 2000-2001 (Box-folder 13:13)